ZHUOWAN LI

https://lizw14.github.io 410-900-2393 \(\) lizhuowan14@gmail.com

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in computer vision and natural language processing, including multimodal models, vision-and-language, compositional reasoning, model robustness, etc. I have experience in pretrained LLMs/VLMs. I am always excited to explore topics like generative AI, embodied AI and foundation models.

EDUCATION

Johns Hopkins University

2018 - 2024

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Advisors: Alan Yuille, Benjamin Van Durme

Thesis: On the Diagnosis and Generalization of Compositional Visual Reasoning. 2024.

Tsinghua University

2014 - 2018

B.E. in Electronic Information Science and Technology

Second major: Journalism and Communication

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Google Research, Mountain View, CA

Feb 2024 - Present

Software Engineer

· Personalization of using large language models using retrieval-augmented generation.

Amazon AWS, Santa Clara, CA

May 2023 - Nov 2023

Applied scientist intern. Mentors: Bhavan Jasani, Peng Tang, Shabnam Ghadar

· Compositional reasoning for document visual question answering using LLMs (in CVPR 2024).

Facebook, Menlo Park, CA

May 2021 - September 2021

Research intern. Mentors: Dhruv Mahajan

· Unsupervised domain adaptation with guidance of pretrained models.

Adobe Research, San Jose, CA

May 2019 - Nov 2019

Research intern. Mentors: Quan Tran, Long Mai, Zhe Lin

· Propose new datasets and methods for a new task: context-aware group captioning (in CVPR 2020).

Sensetime, Beijing, China

Oct 2017 - March 2018

Part-time research intern. Mentor: Shuai Yi

· Learn discriminative human representations by reconstructing multi-view images using GAN (in NeruIPS 2018).

Tsinghua University, Beijing, China

Nov 2016 - May 2017

Research Assistant. Advisor: Prof. Shengjin Wang

· Improve person re-identification with fine-grained attributes and pose information.

PUBLICATIONS

ExoViP: Step-by-step Verification and Exploration with Exoskeleton Modules for Compositional Visual Reasoning

Yuxuan Wang, Alan Yuille, **Zhuowan Li***, Zilong Zheng*.

Under submission (2024)

Synthesize Step-by-Step: Tools, Templates and LLMs as Data Generators for Reasoning-Based Chart VQA.

Zhuowan Li*, Bhavan Jasani*, Peng Tang, Shabnam Ghadar.

CVPR 2024

Causal-CoG: A Causal-Effect Look at Context Generation for Boosting Multi-modal Language Models Shitian Zhao, **Zhuowan Li**, YadongLu, Alan Yuille, Yan Wang.

CVPR 2024 **Highlight**

Localization vs. Semantics: Visual Representations in Unimodal and Multimodal Models **Zhuowan Li**, Cihang Xie, Benjamin Van Durme, Alan Yuille.

EACL 2024

3D-Aware Visual Question Answering about Parts, Poses and Occlusions.

Xingrui Wang, Wufei Ma, Zhuowan Li, Adam Kortylewski, Alan Yuille.

NeurIPS 2023

Super-CLEVR: A Virtual Benchmark to Diagnose Domain Robustness in Visual Reasoning.

Zhuowan Li, Xingrui Wang, Elias Stengel-Eskin, Adam Kortylewski, Wufei Ma, Benjamin Van Durme, Alan Yuille.

CVPR 2023 Highlight

Visual Commonsense in Pretrained Unimodal and Multimodal Models.

Chenyu Zhang, Benjamin Van Durme, **Zhuowan Li***, Elias Stengel-Eskin*.

NAACL 2022 Oral

SwapMix: Diagnosing and Regularizing the Over-Reliance on Visual Context in Visual Question Answering.

Vipul Gupta, **Zhuowan Li**, Adam Kortylewski, Chenyu Zhang, Yingwei Li, Alan Yuille.

CVPR 2022

Calibrating Concepts and Operations: Towards Symbolic Reasoning on Real Images.

Zhuowan Li, Elias Stengel-Eskin, Yixiao Zhang, Cihang Xie, Quan Tran, Benjamin Van Durme, Alan Yuille. *ICCV 2021*

Context-Aware Group Captioning via Self-Attention and Contrastive Features.

Zhuowan Li, Quan Tran, Long Mai, Zhe Lin, Alan Yuille.

CVPR 2020.

FD-GAN: Pose-guided Feature Distilling GAN for Robust Person Re-identification.

Yixiao Ge*, **Zhuowan Li***, Haiyu Zhao, Guojun Yin, Shuai Yi, Xiaogang Wang, Hongsheng Li.

NeurIPS 2018

PATENTS

Contrastive Captioning for Image Groups. Patent no. US 20240037939A1, 2024/2/1 Quan Tran, Long Mai, Zhe Lin, **Zhuowan Li**.

TALKS

Towards	Generali	zable	Visual	Reasoning
iowaius	Generan	Zabie	v isuai	rteasoning

<u> </u>	
- Google Research	Nov 2023
- Horizon Robotics	Oct 2023
- Tiktok	Oct 2023
- UC Santa Cruz	Sep 2023
- MIT: Computational Cognitive Science Group (Josh Tenenbaum's group)	May 2023

AWARDS

CVPR 2023 Doctoral Consortium

MENTORING

Vipul Gupta	visiting intern, now PhD at Penn State University
Chenyu Heidi Zhang	JHU undergrad, now master at Stanford University
Chenyu Zhang	JHU master, now PhD at University of Trento

Xingrui Wang USC master, now PhD at JHU

Varun Iyer JHU master

Shitian Zhao visiting undergrad from ECNU

Yijiang Li JHU master student

Yuxuan Wang visiting master student from Peking University

TEACHING

EN.601.461/661. Computer Vision

Johns Hopkins University

Spring 2022

Role: Teaching Assistant Instructor: Kapil Katyal

SERVICE

Reviewer for CVPR, ICCV, ECCV, NeurIPS, ICML, ICLR.

SKILLS

Programming LanguagesPython, MATLAB, C++, C, IATEXDeep Learning ToolsPytorch, Tensorflow, Torch, Caffe